Hi, this is Matt Baker. As you've
probably heard by now, Paramount is
taking over Warner Brothers, which means
that the media landscape in the US is
about to change in a major way. But, you
know, big media mergers like this are
actually nothing new. They've been going
on for decades, and in fact, at some
level, go all the way back to the very
beginning. Therefore, I decided to chart
it all out. And in today's video, I'm
going to go through the chart in detail,
and basically explain to you the entire
history of the American TV and film
industry.
The very first movie made in Hollywood
was In Old California, released in 1910.
It was, of course, a silent movie, as
the technology for matching up sound
with moving pictures had not yet been
perfected. The producer was the Biograph
Company, which at the time was the
leading maker of silent films, most of
which had previously been made in New
York. However, during the 1910s, several
companies started making films in
Hollywood, and pretty soon, it was the
center of the American movie-making
business. Although Biograph did not
survive, many of the other companies
from this silent movie era did, many of
them merging with each other to form
major studios. For example, there were
once three separate studios named Metro
Pictures, Goldwyn Pictures, and Louis B.
Mayer Pictures. In 1924, all three were
bought by the Loews theater chain and
merged to form MGM. Likewise, what was
originally Fox Film eventually merged
with 20th Century Pictures to form 20th
Century Fox. However, the oldest
Hollywood merger is the one between
Famous Players, the Jesse Lasky Company,
and a distributor called Paramount.
Originally called Famous Players-Lasky,
it eventually changed its name to
Paramount, which is what it's known as
today. It claims as its start date May
8th, 1912, as that was when Famous
Players was founded. However, Universal
Pictures was founded just 1 week
earlier, on April 30th, 1912. Thus,
Universal gets to claim the distinction
of being the oldest surviving film
studio in Hollywood. Also starting out
during the silent movie era was
Cohn-Brandt-Cohn,
later known as Columbia Pictures, as
well as Warner Brothers, which was, in
fact, started by four brothers with the
last name Warner. Now, interestingly,
Samuel Goldwyn, Louis Mayer, Marcus
Loew, William Fox, Adolph Zukor, founder
of Famous Players, Jesse Lasky, Carl
Laemmle, founder of Universal, Joe
Brandt, the two Cohns, and the four
Warners all had one thing in common.
Well, besides the fact that they were
all men, and that is that they were all
Jewish. Now, why was this? Well, the
main reason is that most of the
well-established industries at that time
didn't want to hire Jews, and therefore,
Jews, most of whom had just recently
immigrated to the US, were forced to
become entrepreneurs. The film industry
at the time was in its very early
stages, and not yet a big money-maker,
and therefore, it was one of the few
industries open to newcomers. Now, does
this mean that the popular notion of
Jews controlling Hollywood is true?
Well, it is certainly true that Jews
were instrumental in creating Hollywood,
but it's not true that they somehow
control it today. This is because, as
we'll see, most of these small studios
ended up, over time, becoming controlled
by huge multinational corporations, each
of which is now led by more diverse
leadership teams. Now, continuing along
the top of the chart, we next come to
First National, which was eventually
bought out by Warner Brothers. They
owned the rights to several films
starring Charlie Chaplin, who was, by
far, the most famous actor of the silent
movie period. However, Chaplin also
started his own company, United Artists,
together with two other leading actors
from early Hollywood, Mary Pickford and
Douglas Fairbanks, who actually got
married, as well as D.W. Griffith, the
famous director known for his
controversial film The Birth of a
Nation. The idea behind United Artists
was to give actors more control over
their films. Finally, there was FBO
Pictures, which stood for Film Booking
Offices. This one was eventually
controlled by none other than Joseph P.
Kennedy, the father of JFK. He ended up
merging it with several vaudeville
companies to create RKO, the R standing
for Radio, and the K and O standing for
Keith and Orpheum, which were two
vaudeville companies. Now, what was
vaudeville? Well, vaudeville was
basically what people went to the
theaters to watch before movies. It
consisted of live acts, such as singing,
dancing, and comedy, combined together
into a single show, and priced so that
the average person could afford a
ticket. Many of the earliest Hollywood
actors had previously been vaudeville
performers. Next up, I'm going to talk
about the transition from silent movies
to movies with talking. The first movie
to incorporate some talking was The Jazz
Singer, produced by Warner Brothers in
1927. After this, most of the other
studios followed suit and started to
shift away from silent movies and
towards talkies, which meant movies with
sound. Take note, however, that the
switch didn't happen overnight, as it
took some time for the industry to
adapt. And thus, for several years, most
studios created both types of films.
This transition period is also known as
the pre-Code era, being a reference to
the Hays Code, which was not enforced
until 1934. Basically, the Hays Code was
a list of rules that movie makers had to
follow, such as no profanity and no
sexually explicit material. By 1934, the
switch from transition to sound was
basically complete, and the golden age
of Hollywood had begun. So, take note
that it was during the '30s, '40s, and
'50s that all of those classic black and
white movies were made. And for the most
part, they were made by just eight major
studios, the five biggest being MGM,
20th Century Fox, Paramount, Warner
Brothers, and RKO. Take note that Disney
was not considered a major studio during
this classic period, as it was still
almost entirely focused on animation
during these early years. Now, it's
impossible to talk about classic
Hollywood without bringing up what's
called the studio system. You see, back
then, unlike today, actors tended to
have contracts with only one studio. So,
for example, Greta Garbo and Clark Gable
worked for MGM, Shirley Temple and
Marilyn Monroe for 20th Century Fox, Mae
West and Bob Hope for Paramount, Bette
Davis and Humphrey Bogart for Warner
Brothers, and Fred Astaire and Katharine
Hepburn for RKO, although they both
later moved to MGM. Only a few big-name
actors, such as Cary Grant and Jimmy
Stewart, were able to become
freelancers. Another aspect of the
studio system was that the big
production companies also owned their
own theater chains, and thus, were able
to make extra money off of exclusive
premieres, while forcing independent
theaters to buy their movies alongside
their major hits, something called block
booking. However, in a 1948 ruling
called the Paramount Decree, the US
Supreme Court made it illegal for
studios to practice block booking, as
well as to own their own theater chains.
Thus, for example, MGM and Loews were
forced to split into two separate
companies. This important ruling set the
stage for the demise of classic
Hollywood, but there was actually
something else that ended up being the
final nail in the coffin, the growing
popularity of television. So, let's now
switch over to the other side of the
chart and talk about that. Of course,
before television came radio, around the
same time that the first talking movies
came out. The main difference being that
you had to go to the cinema to watch a
movie, whereas with radio, the shows
were broadcast over the air and could be
picked up at home. The first major
broadcasting company to be established
was NBC. Originally, it operated two
networks, each of which consisted of
several radio stations connected
together. The main network, which aired
the popular sponsored shows, was called
NBC Red, whereas the secondary network,
which was commercial-free and mostly had
news and educational programs, was
called NBC Blue. The National
Broadcasting Company's main competitor,
established just 1 year later, was the
Columbia Broadcasting System, or CBS. It
had no connection to Columbia Pictures,
though. There was also a third radio
network called Mutual, which was
originally run as a co-op.
It never did make the transition to
television, though, and ceased to exist
in the '90s. However, because of
concerns that NBC exerted too much
control over the industry, the
government forced NBC to sell its Blue
Network in 1943. It then rebranded as
the American Broadcasting Company, or
ABC, and thus, the stage was set for the
US to get three major TV networks. Now,
the transition from radio to television
did not happen overnight. NBC began
doing TV broadcasts over the air in
1939, CBS in 1941, and ABC in 1948. But,
they were all still doing radio
broadcasts at the same time. It wasn't
until the mid-'50s that most homes in
the US owned a television set, and thus
it wasn't until around then that the
three big networks switched their main
focus from radio to television. Now,
there was also originally a fourth
network called DuMont that never did do
radio, but instead started directly with
television. They, however, ceased
operations just when things were really
taking off. So, yeah, from the mid-50s
to the late '80s, television mostly went
out over the air and was dominated by
just three channels. Now, like with the
film industry, the government didn't
want these three companies to become
monopolies. So, in 1970, one of the
things they did was to establish a new
rule whereby networks were no longer
allowed to own the shows they aired
during prime time. This led to the
creation of several new companies, the
most important of which was Viacom,
which was spun off from CBS in '71.
We'll be coming back to them later
because eventually the rule gets
dropped. Now, as you probably know, all
television programming was originally in
black and white. So, when did the switch
to color take place? Well, it depends.
On the network side, the change occurred
around 1966,
but on the consumer side, that didn't
really mean anything unless you owned a
color TV. And it wasn't until the
mid-'70s that most homes in America had
at least one of those.
Let's now go back to Hollywood to see
how it adapted to the new situation.
Like I mentioned earlier, the classic
era in Hollywood came to an end during
the 1950s, with most of the big studios
being forced to downsize. In fact, in
the case of RKO, they shut down
altogether, eventually selling most of
their library to United Artists. Warner
Brothers actually had to do something
similar. They were able to continue
making movies, but opted to sell their
pre-1950 library in order to make some
quick cash.
They sold it to a company called
Associated Artists, but then this was in
turn sold to United Artists. But the
swapping of film rights didn't end there
because eventually United Artists was
bought by MGM.
So, by the time we get to the Hollywood
Renaissance, also known as New
Hollywood, there were now only six
surviving major studios, plus Disney,
which had grown considerably. The
starting point for the New Hollywood era
is usually given as being around 1967.
There are several reasons for this, but
the main one is that by this point, all
of the original directors from the
earliest days of film were gone, and
there was now a new generation that had
risen up to take their place. But there
were some other key changes as well,
such as the switch to color and the end
of the Hays Code, which in 1968 was
replaced by a rating system whereby
films were now rated as being either G,
PG, R, or X. Finally, the New Hollywood
era saw the rise of a bunch of new
independent film studios, such as New
Line Cinema, Lucasfilm, Orion Pictures,
TriStar Pictures, and Castle Rock
Entertainment. But take note, this is by
no means an exhaustive list. I chose
these five as examples because they're
going to show up again later.
Okay, next up is what I've called the
cable TV  consolidation era. And
this is where things get really fun.
First of all, let me talk about the
transition from over-the-air TV to cable
TV, during which time the US went from
just three main channels to hundreds.
Although cable was used as far back as
the '40s to bring TV signals to remote
areas, its more widespread use began in
New York City, where the steady growth
of skyscrapers was starting to impact TV
reception. This led a company to start
building hardwired connections between
buildings so that residents could get
programs, particularly sports, through
reliable cables instead of having to use
antennas. They also had the idea to
offer movies this way, which resulted in
the creation of HBO, or Home Box Office,
which was quickly bought out by Time
Inc., the publishers of Time magazine.
As more and more cities started to build
local cable networks, HBO started to
connect them together using satellites,
and thus the modern cable TV era was
born.
Now, two of the most important figures
during this period were Ted Turner and
Rupert Murdoch. Turner created TBS in
1976, but then more importantly, CNN in
1980. From there, he managed to acquire
the rights to MGM's massive library by
buying the studio and then selling it
back without the library. This was
important because, remember, MGM's
library included not only MGM's content,
but also United Artists, RKO's, and
everything made by Warner Brothers prior
to 1950. All of this content allowed
Turner to create even more channels,
such as TNT and the Cartoon Network.
Finally, he bought two small studios,
New Line Cinema and Castle Rock. So,
yeah, by the mid-'90s, Ted Turner was
definitely one of the biggest media
moguls on the scene.
But let's now back up a bit and talk
about Rupert Murdoch. As you know, up to
this point, the US had only three major
TV networks, NBC, CBS, and ABC. Murdoch
wanted to create a fourth, so he did two
things. First, he bought a bunch of the
assets that used to be owned by DuMont.
Then he bought a major studio, 20th
Century Fox. It was for this reason that
he decided to call his new channel Fox,
launching it in 1986.
But keep in mind, Fox was different from
all of the new cable TV channels popping
up. Like the original three, Fox was
first and foremost a traditional
over-the-air network, even though most
people eventually accessed it via cable,
as they did NBC, CBS, and ABC. Now, due
to the popularity of CNN, Fox decided to
launch its own cable news network, Fox
News, in '96. NBC also launched a news
channel that year in partnership with
Microsoft, hence the name MSNBC,
although take note, Microsoft eventually
dropped out.
Let's now go back to HBO, which in 1990
merged with Warner Brothers to create
Time Warner. Then, in 1996, it bought
Ted Turner's company, making Time Warner
at the time the largest media
conglomerate in the world. Now,
remember, Turner, among other things,
owned the pre-1950 Warner Brothers
library. So, basically at this point,
Warner got all of its content back.
Now, I'm not going to talk about every
single cable channel that launched
during this period because, like I said,
there were hundreds. But let me point
out a few other important ones, such as
ESPN, which to this day is the most
popular sports channel on cable. It
launched in 1979 and was then acquired
by ABC in 1984. Then, of course, there's
MTV, which stands for Music Television.
While not as popular today, during the
'80s and '90s, it was hugely
influential, especially among teens and
young adults, as well as Nickelodeon,
the first ever channel for children.
These two channels were originally both
projects started by Warner Brothers, but
were eventually both sold to Viacom,
that spin-off company from CBS that I
mentioned earlier. It continued to grow,
and about a decade later managed to buy
Paramount. Which now brings me to the
three most important mergers on this
chart, all of which happened within a
period of just eight years. The first
was Disney's purchase of ABC in 1996.
This combined for the very first time
one of the three original TV networks
with a major film studio. Of course,
once that happened, the other two
networks had to get paired up as well.
So, in 1999, CBS merged with Paramount
as the result of CBS and Viacom being
reunited. And then in 2004, NBC merged
with Universal. So, that explains why on
this chart I started both NBC and
Universal in red, CBS and Paramount in
green, and ABC and Disney in blue. Now,
you've probably noticed that 20th
Century Fox is also blue rather than
purple, and that's because our story
isn't quite done yet. But right now, let
me just point out that everything in
yellow ended up as part of Time Warner.
So, that takes care of all of the big
studios except one, Columbia Pictures.
It, along with TriStar Pictures, was
purchased by Sony, and therefore today
it is Sony Pictures that is the fifth
major studio.
Now, before I get to the streaming era,
I need to briefly talk about VHS tapes
and DVDs because until streaming, they
were the main way that people watched
movies at home. VHS tapes were invented
in the 1970s, but didn't become
mainstream until the '80s, which is when
Blockbuster Video was founded, quickly
becoming the main movie rental company
in the US. Then, during the mid-'90s,
DVDs were invented, and within five
years they had surpassed VHS as the main
way that movies were sold and rented,
which brings me to Netflix, which was
founded in 1997.
Originally, it was just a movie rental
service that sent DVDs out by mail. But
then in 2007, Netflix became the first
major streaming service. After they
launched, they were quickly followed by
Amazon Video on Demand and a joint
venture between several companies called
Hulu. For the next 10 years, these three
streaming services were basically the
only ones available. Of course, there
was also YouTube, but YouTube's always
been a little bit different, focusing
more on independent creators like
UsefulCharts.
But then, starting around 2020, things
began to change with lots more streaming
services popping up but at the same time
more media consolidation taking place.
In fact, if the Paramount Warner
Brothers deal goes through and it looks
like it will the US will be left with
just three really big media companies
alongside five medium-sized ones. So to
finish up this video, let me now go
through each of these companies one by
one and highlight some of the final
mergers and launches that took place to
bring us to where we are today. Let's
start with Comcast. Originally just a
cable TV and internet provider, it
bought NBC Universal in 2011 meaning
that it now owns one of the three big TV
networks plus a major film studio. On
top of this they also own two major
animation studios, Illumination the
makers of Despicable Me and DreamWorks
the makers of Shrek. However, as the
mascot for this company, I actually
chose to use Woody Woodpecker who has
been associated with Universal since the
1940s. Other Comcast franchises include
Wicked, Jurassic Park and one that goes
all the way back to 1913 the Universal
Monsters which includes the rights to
certain ways of depicting Dracula and
Frankenstein. This explains why movies
made by other companies have to make
these characters look quite a bit
different from the standard depictions.
Now when it comes to streaming platforms
Comcast does have one although it's near
to the bottom of the list in terms of
popularity. Launched in 2020 it's called
Peacock a reference to the NBC logo.
Finally, I should mention that last year
Comcast announced that it would be
spinning off most of its cable TV assets
into a new separate company called
Versant. Most notably this includes
MSNBC which has now rebranded as MS Now.
Let's now jump to Disney represented of
course by Mickey Mouse. Like I said
earlier Disney now owns ABC which means
that it also owns ESPN. But their
acquisitions didn't stop there. In 2006
they bought the animation studio Pixar
famous for making Toy Story and Cars.
Interestingly it had actually started
out as a division of Lucasfilm. Next up
Disney bought Marvel in 2009 and then
Lucasfilm itself in 2012. This gave
Disney the rights to the Avengers as
well as to Star Wars the two most
profitable live-action movie franchises
ever. However, take note that after
Mickey Mouse Disney's most valuable
asset is actually Winnie the Pooh the
rights to which they bought all the way
back in 1961.
Finally in 2019 Disney bought 20th
Century Fox giving it a second major
studio. But take note the deal did not
include the Fox TV channel nor Fox News.
Those remain separate which we'll get to
later. It did however include the
National Geographic Channel which 20th
Century Fox had acquired in 2015. So on
Disney's streaming service Disney Plus
you can access everything I've mentioned
so far and soon it will also incorporate
Hulu content since Disney also now has a
controlling stake in it. Okay, let's now
look at Paramount represented by Bugs
Bunny the main cartoon character
associated with Warner Brothers. Now
like I mentioned earlier CBS and
Paramount first merged in 1999. But what
I didn't mention was that in 2005 they
split up again. Paramount became a part
of the new Viacom whereas CBS became
independent. This situation lasted until
2019 which is when they got back
together again under the name Paramount
Global. But then Paramount Global was
bought by Skydance a company founded by
David Ellison who is the son of Larry
Ellison currently the second richest
person in America after Elon Musk. It
was David Ellison who desperately wanted
Warner Brothers and finally beat out
Netflix for it just last week. This
means that he will now soon control a
second major film studio as well as
several additional TV channels. The two
most important being CNN and HBO.
Although it's yet to be seen how they
will be incorporated into the company.
But perhaps even more importantly
because of the Warner Brothers
acquisition Paramount will now have
control of some of the most valuable
media franchises in the world including
Harry Potter, Lord of the Rings, Game of
Thrones and DC Comics the creators of
Batman. This on top of Star Trek and all
the various Nickelodeon franchises which
they already owned. It's likely that all
this content will eventually be
incorporated into their streaming
platform Paramount Plus.
So it looks like in the years ahead
Paramount and Disney are going to become
major rivals as much of their content
pretty much now mirrors each other. For
example, Paramount has Star Trek Disney
has Star Wars. Paramount has DC Comics.
Disney has Marvel Comics. Paramount has
Nickelodeon and now Looney Tunes and
everything associated with the Cartoon
Network. Disney has the Disney Channel
and all of the various Disney cartoons.
Paramount has Discovery. Disney has
National Geographic. The list could go
on.
Now in addition to the new big three
there are also now five medium-sized
companies to discuss. Like I said Fox
has remained independent and it now has
its own streaming platform Fox One. Then
of course there's Netflix which almost
became the new owners of Warner
Brothers. But even without Warner
Brothers it is still at least for now
the most popular streaming service in
the US. Right now it's most valuable
media franchise is Stranger Things. In
terms of major film studios the only big
one remaining other than the ones owned
by Comcast Paramount and Disney is Sony
which like I said earlier bought
Columbia. They now offer a streaming
service called Sony Pictures Core but it
is only available through Sony products
such as PlayStations, Sony TVs and Sony
phones. Now one thing I want to mention
about Sony is that they own the film
rights to Spider-Man even though
Spider-Man is a part of the Marvel
Universe which is owned by Disney. This
is because prior to Disney buying Marvel
Marvel sold the rights to Spider-Man to
Sony back in 1999.
Let me now talk about MGM because
although Ted Turner acquired the rights
to everything it had made up until 1986
the company did continue after that as a
smaller studio. That's why after 86 it's
shown over here as a thinner and now
green line. Take note that in 1997 MGM
bought Orion Pictures but then in 2021
Amazon bought MGM. So now Amazon owns
one of the original Hollywood studios
even though it's nowhere near as
influential as it once was. Currently
the most valuable movie franchise still
owned by MGM is James Bond.
Finally there's Apple TV the streaming
service owned by Apple. But although
Apple is obviously a huge company
they're still mainly a tech company and
so far not all that big in terms of
media ownership although they do own the
rights to the Peanuts franchise.
Okay, so that was a look at the US TV
and film industry and how things
continue to consolidate into the hands
of fewer and fewer companies. Let me
know if you think I missed anything
important because as time goes on I'll
keep the chart updated and perhaps do
more videos on it whenever major changes
occur. Thanks for watching.